So here’s the thing
然后是这样
all those born before 2002
那个所有在2002年之前
are considered to be under 18 years old
是这个18岁以下的小孩的人呢
In my eyes, everyone looks like a kid.
在我眼里看的都是小孩
Of course, you were born after 2002.
当然来讲你是2002年之后出生来讲
To me,
对我来说呢
you're even more of a kid.
你更是小孩
Because something happened in 2002.
因为2002年发生了一件事情
I turned 18.
我18岁了
So from that year on, I was an adult.
所以那一年开始我就是一个成年人了哈
Enough with the small talk,
呃废话不说
let's get back to today's topic.
咱们继续今天的话题
Don't pity others.
就是你不要可怜别人啊
Those who elicit pity often have their own faults.
可怜之人必有可恨之处
If you're someone who others often need to rely on,
如果你是一个别人经常需要啊
a person in need,
可怜的人
frequently asking you for help,
经常需要找你做帮忙的话
then there might be issues with your character.
那你这个人本身的人格是有问题的啊
Many people say I'm generous and kind,
很多人说我乐善好施
I actively help others, What's wrong with that? But let me tell you, When I talk about it a lot, There's a difference between kindness and true kindness.
我积极帮助别人 这有什么错 但是我跟你讲啊 我和很多的时候来讲的话 这个善良和真正的善良之间是有区别的啊
Why is there a difference between kindness and true kindness?
为什么说善良跟真正的善良之间是有区别的
When you do something,
就是你做这件事情
Many people's motives for doing good are,
很多人做好事的动机是啊
To go to heaven after I die,
我死了以后能上天堂啊
Or after I die,
或者我死了以后啊
These things can spare me from the suffering of the six realms of rebirth.
这些东西能让我啊不再受六道轮回之苦
I don't care about your beliefs.
我我不管你的信仰是什么吧
A lot of people have different beliefs, you know.
啊很多人的信仰是怎么着呢
But in the end, it's all about good karma.
就是总之这是福报
So I want to do good deeds.
所以我要干好事
But this is similar to accumulating currency,
那你这个东西跟积累货币啊
or building up credit, really.
跟积累信用这东西没有什么区别啊
It's still a form of utilitarian behavior.
这还是一种功利行为
And when it comes to the motives behind many people doing good deeds,
甚至很多人做好事的动机来讲的话
it's often shaped by their parents' influence.
就是他父母给他形成了这种人格嗯
So, tell him that doing good is the right thing.
所以呢就告诉他做好事是对的
He's just doing what's right.
所以他只是在做正确的事
He hasn't really made a choice in his life.
他不是真正经过自己的人生的选择
Whether to do good or to do wrong.
决定去从善还是作恶啊
If we talk about the good deeds you do out of habit, It's a behavioral habit of yours. Or you were taught from a young age to do good. Fundamentally speaking, You're essentially no different from someone who doesn't do good. Do you know why I'm saying this? There are a lot of so-called good people in this world.
俗惯你所做的这些好事来讲的话 是你的一个行为习惯 或者你从小就被教唆了要做好事 那本质上来讲 其实你就跟没做好事是一样的 你知道我为什么会说呢 这个世界上是有很多烂好人的
They think to themselves,
就是他们自以为
that they are doing good deeds,
然后我再做好事
like releasing animals in places where it causes biological disasters.
比如去一些社会造成生物灾害的地方去放生啊
They do things like that.
就干这种事儿
Many people think they are doing good,
很多人自以为的在干好事
helping others,
在帮助别人
engaging in poverty alleviation.
在扶贫
Volunteering as a teacher
在支教
Of course, I mean many people go to help with poverty alleviation
当然我是说很多人去扶贫
To volunteer as a teacher
去支教
It’s absolutely a good thing
做的绝对都是好事啊
But I mean, a small number of people don’t have this mindset
但是我是说有一小部分人他的心态不是这样的
Their mindset is that they are good people
他的心态是我是一个好人的设定
So they want to do these things
所以我要去做这种事
Or after doing this, ah
或者这件事情我做了以后啊
What kind of rewards will I get
我会得到什么什么样的回报
Regardless of the moral rewards,
不管是道德上的回报
it's also a form of having an agenda.
这也是一种有所图
You know?
你知道吗
So, for a truly good person,
所以真正一个好人来讲的话
the purpose of doing good is only one:
他做好事的目的只有一个
to make human society a better place.
就是让这个人类社会变得更加美好啊
This is an act of selflessness.
这是一种无私的行为
Once you imagine,
一旦你想象的
for example, I do good deeds because the school will give me recognition.
比如说啊我做好事是因为学校这样会给我荣誉
I'll be given a certificate. And I do this good deed because it makes me feel good inside. So, this is all a form of self-interest, isn't it? It's all about having a selfish motive while doing something public-spirited. Just like many people.
会给我奖状 然后我做这件好事是因为这样我心里很舒服 那你这个东西都是一种利己行为啊 都是一种有公立私的这个私心的行为 就像很多人似的
They have a strong sense of empathy.
他们很有很强的同情心啊
Having a strong sense of empathy can lead to significant issues.
有很强的同情心呢就会引起很大的问题
Because in this society,
因为在这个社会来讲的话
all kinds of people exist.
就是各种各样的人都是有的啊
People can't always be judged by their good or bad deeds.
很多人的好坏不能以这个善恶来评判啊
For example, some people love to take advantage of situations.
比如说有人他爱占便宜啊
Others are fond of cheating.
有人他就爱出老千
Some have a strong aversion to injustice.
有人嫉恶如仇啊
And some are indifferent when it doesn't concern them.
有人就是事不关己
They keep it at arm's length.
高高挂起
Thus, a variety of different values
所以各种各样不同的价值观
shape us into diverse members of society.
让我们形成了各种各样不同的社会成员啊
And due to our different roles and responsibilities,
又因为自己的不同的分工啊
Different levels of wealth
不同的财富等级
Different social strata
不同的社会等级
Have led to the diverse and complex nature of human society
造成了这个人类社会的千变万化
So many people who play the victim
所以很多那种卖可怜的人呢
Are particularly skilled at finding hosts
他是特别会去找宿主的啊
Once you sympathize with their pitiful state
一旦你去可怜这个人的可怜的状态呢
They will start to drain your resources
他就会啊去吸食你的财富
Take up your time And disrupt your emotions So, in the end, to wrap it up It's often said that those who are pitiable have their own faults Many people actually don't deserve our pity
占有你的时间 拨乱你的情绪 然后最后呢啊最终呢来讲的话 他其实呢咱们说可怜之人必有可恨之处 很多人其实并不值得可怜啊
Why do we say these people don't deserve pity?
为什么说这些人不值得可怜呢
How should we approach this issue?
就是说怎么说这个问题呢
It's about their actions
就是说他的一些行为
When we look at their behavior
他的一些东西来讲的话
Frankly speaking, when you consider it
说实在的就是你在看来来讲
You might feel that they are complaining to you
你会觉得啊他跟你诉苦了
You think it's necessary to stand by him
你觉得有必要站在他这一边
But in reality
但实际上来讲
Many people are not truly
很多人他并不是真正意义上的
Honestly, they need to help many people
说实在的是啊需要帮助很多人
He treats complaining like
他对这种诉苦来讲
Like Xiang Linsao
就像祥林嫂一样
It's a habitual act of complaining
他是一种习惯性行为的诉苦啊
Many people aren't really that miserable
就是我们说很多人他并不是有多苦啊
They just choose to endure it
他才去受这个苦
His purpose in complaining is to evoke your sympathy.
他诉苦的目的是激发你的同情心
Then, he tries to latch onto you.
然后呢在寄宿到你身上啊
I see a lot of examples like this around me.
我身边这种例子特别多啊
As you all know, I have a particular fondness for this.
大家也知道我呢比较喜欢这个啊
I'm a person who enjoys being generous and kind.
乐善好施的一个人
Right now, I have two such examples around me. Many people are truly pitiful, Qifeng. How would I put it? If someone is extremely pitiful. I'll be giving you moral support
在我身边现在就有两个这样的例子啊 其实很多人很可怜的奇峰 我是会怎么说呢 啊如果你这人非常非常的可怜 我会是对你进行精神上的鼓励
and even material rewards
甚至物质上的奖励
but recently, the two people I've been helping
但是我最近帮助的两个啊
let's not mention names
咱也别说是谁了吧
you'll notice they turn to me when they're in a really low mood
反正就是你会发现他在情绪很低谷的时候
or when they're in a tough financial spot
他在经济上很落魄的时候
they always think of me
总是想起我来啊
so when they talk about it, they feel that Brother Rong
所以来讲的话就觉得啊荣哥
look at how I manage to do it
你看我怎么怎么样
Then I came across this issue
然后我遇到这种问题呀
I also couldn't find a job
我遇也找不到工作呀
What should I do
我怎么样
And I faced a lot of discrimination at school
然后我在学校备受歧视啊
What can I do
怎么样
You'll notice that when this person has the ball
你会发现这种人他有球的时候
He'll come to you
他会来找你
But when I'm short of money
那我缺钱了啊
I go to Brother Rong
我找荣哥
I'll go and make a report
我去报嘣一下
Old man, drop some gold coins
老头爆点金币啊
I reported and dropped some gold coins
我爆点金币报成了啊
Report a few hundred bucks, right?
报个几百块钱对吧
Then after a while, I couldn't find a job again
然后呢过一段时间哎呀我又找不到工作了
Who can I talk to about my stress?
我压力跟谁说啊
A couple of days later, I found a boyfriend
过两天啊自己找到男朋友了
Then my mood improved
然后呢这个心情好了
And he'll forget about you right away
然后他马上他就会把你忘了
Many people are like that too
很多人也是啊
all day long
在整天啊
like going out in cosplay
比如说出去出cos
often get criticized by others and all sorts of trolls come to bash them so they come to me to vent and I tell them that this is actually quite normal you've actually been doing a great job and if you check back in a couple of days, you'll see Suddenly blocked you So let me tell you
经常被别人骂之类的 然后各种各样的小黑粉去骂他 然后呢就跟我来诉苦 然后我就说其实这东西很正常 你其实做的一直挺好的 然后过两天你再看哎 突然就把你拉黑了 所以我跟你讲
A lot of times, don't go out of your way to help others
很多的时候不要好心去帮助别人啊
Because when you help someone
因为你被帮助
After you've helped them with good intentions
好心被帮助了以后
It might leave you feeling really upset
你可能会让你心情很难受啊
Do things
做一些事情
But when I do these things
但是我做这些事情
Why did I get used to it long ago
为什么我早就习惯了啊
I've supported more than just one or two people.
我资助的不止一两个人
Actually, I've supported around a dozen or so.
我资助了其实大概十几个人吧
Quite a few people.
就是很多人
It's not like I provide massive support.
因为其实也不是说大量资助
I don't just give them tens of thousands of dollars.
不是说我牙给他打几万
It's not like that.
不是这样
Many of them do come from families in real need.
很多人确实家里边比如说很困难
Or they might be recent college graduates struggling to find a job.
或者说大学刚毕业找不到工作
Or something along those lines.
或者怎么样来讲
Really, they did come to see me.
真的有来找我的啊
Of course, I also consider the situation.
当然我也看情况
I'm not saying I help everyone.
我不是说谁我都帮啊
Anyway, I definitely help those who are good-looking, right?
反正肯定是帮好看的对吧
That thing is definitely like that.
那个东西一定是这样
So you'll notice that these people know to come to you.
所以你就会发现这些人就是知道过来找你
You would agree, wouldn't you?
你是会答应的啊
So many times,
所以很多的时候
And when a lot of people talk about it,
而且很多人来讲的话
I couldn’t really talk to you much at first
本来跟你聊不了两句
but then I found out you gave him money
后来发现你给他钱了
Oh
哎
he just comes over to chat with you whenever he has nothing to do
没事就过来跟你聊
the truth is, he’s just trying to get money from you
其实他跟你聊的目的就是为了要你的钱
it’s that simple
就这么简单
so many times when you do something out of kindness you feel sorry for him but when he really needs you, it’s not like that I'm very clear in my mind what this kind of person needs me for it's because no one pays attention to him at this time
所以很多的时候你去一个做一好心去做事情 你觉得他可怜 他需要你的时候不是这样的 我心里很清楚 这种人需要我是干什么的 他就是因为这时候没有人搭理他
normal people wouldn't bother with him
正常人都不会搭理他
he actually went online to find someone
他竟然去网上去找一个
an old man who has nothing to do with his life to complain to
跟他毫无生活毫无关系的一个老头去诉苦
which actually shows what kind of image this person usually has
其实本身也就证明这个人平时在他的朋友圈里
in his circle of friends
是一个什么样的形象啊
many people would say
很多人来讲
Why would wisdom come to me to complain?
为什么智慧也会找我来诉苦
Because he knows I would feel sorry for him.
因为知道我会可怜他啊
I’m not saying there’s anything wrong with that.
我并不是说这么做有什么错啊
I’m not suggesting that everyone who comes to me for help
我也并不是说所有来找我帮助的人
actually has issues.
其实都有问题
It’s not like that.
不是这样
What I’m saying is
我就是在说
if you are someone like this,
如果你是一个这样的人
when others come to you for help,
当别人向你来求助的时候
Do you want to help them?
你是否要帮助你
You need to understand this.
心里要明白啊
Because many people are not worth your help.
因为很多人是不值得你帮的
Many people come to you
很多人之所以来找你
Because they know you have a kind heart.
是因为知道你好心眼儿
You will help them.
你会帮他
That’s why they come to you.
所以来找你
This is where the problem lies.
这就有问题了
It’s about why these people ask you for money.
就是他这些人为什么找你借钱啊
Why did you choose to support him?
为什么找你去资助他
Why did you choose to listen to his emotional issues?
为什么找你去聊他的心理事
Actually, you have been putting in effort. Do you know that? You would go to such lengths to help him. You would give without expecting anything in return. So, from his perspective, you are someone he can take advantage of and bully. Of course, speaking of it, I’m not just being used for nothing.
其实你都是有付出的 你知道吗 你会这样付出 你会无偿于他的回报 所以对于他来讲的话 你就是一个可欺负可利用的对象啊 当然来讲的话 咱们说我并不是白白被人利用
I’m not just being bullied for nothing.
白白被人欺负的现象
I have my own agenda, you know.
我也是有所图的啊
Right?
对不对
I have my own plans.
我也是有所图
That’s perfectly normal.
很正常啊
If you want to get one point from me,
你如果想从我这得到一分
I’ll make sure to get three points back from you.
我就会从你那回到拿到三分
If you want to get five points,
你要是想拿到五分
I'll get a perfect score
我就会拿到十分
That's just how it is
这个东西就是这样
So for me
所以对我来讲的话
Doing good deeds is often an investment
很多的时候做这种好事就是一种投资行为啊
For an investment
对于一种投资行为
It's not that I'm easy to take advantage of or anything
并不是我这人好欺负或者怎么样
But many people will interpret it differently
但是很多人会反过来理解
Let me tell you
我跟你讲
That's human nature
人性就是这样
Many people seem pitiful when you look at them.
就是很多人你看他很可怜啊
It’s not easy for them, being ostracized by others.
看他很不容易被人排挤
But you need to understand why they are being ostracized.
但你要明白他为什么被人排挤
Why is he in such a sorry state?
他为什么可怜他
How did it come to this?
为什么到这一步了
Why does he have so few friends his age?
他为什么同龄的朋友很少
He has to go online to find a stranger,
他要在网上去找一个陌
someone completely unrelated, to talk about these things.
毫不相干的陌生人去说这些东西呢
What do you think of his character in everyday life?
那你觉得他日常当中的人品
When it comes to the reality of it
跟他实际的来讲的话
Is it the same as he describes?
跟他形容的是一样的吗
So many people are very good at playing the victim
所以很多人他很会装可怜
Many people are very skilled at exploiting others' sympathy
很多人他非常会利用别人的同情心
Or taking advantage of others' kindness Once you've actually sent them money a few times Once you start treating them like a true friend When you actually need them You'll find that they're nowhere to be found Buy Bao has already blocked you. He hasn't paid you any attention for a long time. Do you know that? Let others tell you.
或利用别人的善心 等你真给他打几次钱 真拿他当朋友的时候 等你需要他的时候 你会发现别人买都买保安 买保就把你拉黑了 早就不会理你了 你知道吗 别人来讲
She's found her happiness with someone else.
人家找到人的幸福了
Why would she need a crutch anymore?
人家干嘛还要找拐棍儿呢
She's already regained her ability to walk.
人家已经恢复了行走能力了啊
She even has a boyfriend supporting her now.
都有男朋友资助她了
Why would she look for a crutch like you?'
怎么还会有你找你一个拐棍儿呢
So, you people who always have a thing for young girls,
所以跟你说你们这些啊总是喜欢小姑娘的人
you can actually learn a few things from me.
其实也从我这儿可以明白一些道理
When you help others,
很多的时候你去对别人的帮助
you must remember,
你一定要记住
if you approach it this way,
如果你这样来讲
without any ulterior motives,
真的是没有所图的
you won't feel bad inside.
你心里边就不会难受
Of course,
是当然来讲
if you always expect something in return from the other person,
如果你总是期望对方会给你回报
More to say
更多的话
The other party isn't a fool either
白对方也不是傻子
They also know you're helping them for a reason
对方也知道你帮助他来讲
You have your own agenda
你也是有目的的
So it's a case of one party willing to give and the other willing to take
所以这个东西就是一个愿打一个愿挨的事
Once you invest
你只要投资了
You have to accept that there's a risk of failure
你就要承认投资有可能会失败
Once you've invested
一旦你投资了
You'll understand it's a mutual game of influence and control
你就会明白这是一种相互的较量跟控制
So, fundamentally speaking,
所以从本质上来讲的话
your actions aren't really doing good,
你这样的行为也不是在做好事
the other party is begging for your pity,
对方祈求你的可怜
he's taking things from you,
他从你这去弄东西
and he's not doing good either, so what's wrong with a thief catching a thief? right? on the surface, he seems pitiful, and it looks like you're willing to help the unfortunate. Neither of you is wrong
他也不是在做好事 所以黑吃黑有什么错呢 对吧 表面上看起来他很可怜 表面上看起来你愿意帮助可怜的人啊 你们俩都没有错
Both of you are good people
你们俩都是善人
That's why many guys are willing to help girls for free
所以这就讲到了很多男生愿意免费给女生帮忙
Is your real intention to help him?
你的目的当然真的是帮他吗
Is your intention to be kind-hearted?
你的目的是你心善吗
Isn't it still about that thing?
你不是还是为了那个啥嘛
So, if you separate certain things from sex
所以说有些东西你要是一旦跟姓啊分辨开啊
This has nothing to do with sex
这东西跟性没关系
I think that's all unreliable
那我觉得都是不可信的
So, in many cases,
所以很多的时候来讲
we say people have an agenda,
我们说人有所图
once you have an agenda,
一旦你有所图
you're not doing good for its own sake,
你就不是在做好事
you're making a purposeful investment.
你就是在有目的的进行投资
I know that my actions are driven by an agenda,
我知道我这些行为是有所图的
I consider this to be an investment.
我认为这就是投资行为
But for me,
但对我来说
helping 100 people
帮100个人
33 people betrayed me
33个人背叛我
About 50 people later went silent
50几个人后来没消息了
There could be a dozen or so
有能十几个
Twenty or so
20几个
It’s already good if this person can show gratitude
这个人能够感恩就已经不错了
To me
对我来说
This is an issue of return on investment
这就是一个投资回报率的问题
So for me, it’s a numbers game
嗯所以对我来说是一个数字问题啊
Of course
当然来讲的话
If you come across such a freeloader, you'd be pretty upset too, but that's just how it is. Even the landlord has no surplus grain. In many cases, when it comes to the behavior of such people, you need to understand, you should know that throughout history,
你遇到了这种白眼狼的话 你也会很生气啊 但是就是这样啊 地主家也没有余粮 很多的时候来讲的话 其实这种人的行为来讲的话 你要明白 你要知道自古以来我说了
men have deceived for pleasure.
男骗色
Scamming for money is always like this with women.
女骗财永远都是这样
They'll act pitiful and ask you for some money to spend.
女生跟你可怜巴巴的跟你要几个钱花
To them,
对于人家来讲的话
it’s a process of honing their acting skills.
那是一个锻炼演技的过程
But truly pitiful people generally won’t ask you for money, you see.
而真正可怜的人一般不会向你开口明白吗
Truly pitiful people internalize their struggles.
真正可怜的人会内化
They blame themselves.
会怪自己
They try to find a way to take control of their own lives.
会想办法去找掌握自己一个办法
And those who ask you for money
而且向你去要钱的人
Do you think others will only ask you for money?
你也觉得别人只会向你一个人要钱吗
Once someone successfully gets money from you,
别人一旦从你这儿要钱要成功了以后
they learn this trick,
他掌握这种技巧
they get a taste of this easy success,
掌握这种痛快的感觉以后
and they fall into a dark path.
他就堕入魔道了
They will move on to the next target.
他就会往下一个路线走了啊
This person will realize,
这个人就会发现诶
I can use my looks,
原来我可以靠自己的姿色
I can use my body to make money.
可以靠自己的身体赚到钱啊
So this is one of the most interesting aspects of human life.
所以这个就是人世间的一个非常有意思的事情
Once he makes money from me in this way,
一旦他通过这种方式赚到我钱
once he makes money from men,
赚到过男人的钱
he’s on a path he can never turn back from.
她就永远走上了一条不归路
Once you take it the first time,
一旦你拿了第一次
you’ll keep taking it.
你就会一直拿下去
This is the essence of human nature. So don’t talk about these patrons of yours, how do you think you are? You're trying to impress others, right? Don't talk about the people holding that money. What do you think? These people deserve it. But in the end, money will corrupt your soul.
所以这就是人性的本质 所以既不要说你这些供养者 你觉得你怎么样 你是为了上人家对吧 你也不要说拿着这些钱的人 你觉得怎么样 这些人都是活该 但是最终他会腐蚀你的灵魂的金钱
It can corrupt a person very quickly.
腐蚀人的速度是很快的
So, all of you who think you're doing good deeds,
所以你们这些自以为在做好事
And not getting rewarded for it,
然后没有得到好报的人
You need to first understand what a good reward is.
你首先要明白好报是什么
You're trying to take off someone's underwear
你图的是扒人家裤衩子
So did you or didn't you take it off?
所以你到底扒没扒
If you did
你扒了的话
then you were making an investment
那你就是在做一件投资行为
so don't think you're doing a good deed
所以不要觉得自己做了好事
putting in your sincere effort
付出了真心
and the other person doesn't give you anything in return
别人没有给你回报
What is the return from others?
那别人给你回报是什么
Are they messing with you?
作你吗啊
Would you like me to stay with you while you sleep?
陪你睡觉吗
Is that so?
是不是
So, quite often,
所以很多的时候
and others might have already done these things,
而且别人可能已经做了这些事情了
then what you’re doing is a form of consumption,
那你这就是一种消费行为了
so don’t think you’re doing a good deed,
所以不要觉得自己在做善事
if you don’t get anything in return,
没有得到回报
quite often, your efforts are driven by a purpose,
很多的时候你的付出你是有目的的
so don’t do it like that.
所以就不要这样
And when others speak this way,
而且别人这样来讲的话
it’s also a form of self-defense.
也是一种自我防卫行为
If he can swindle money from you,
他能从你这坑到钱
he can swindle money from others too.
他就能从别人那坑到钱
But in the end, he’s the one who will suffer the most.
但是最终以后坑的还是他自己
So what’s wrong with such behavior? Who among you is truly the bad guy? And who is truly the good guy? In the eyes of the heavens, Who among you is the good person? And who is the bad person? So don't think everything is about gender opposition. Everything isn't like that.
所以这样的行为有什么错呢 你们谁又真正是坏人呢 谁又真正是好人呢 在老天爷眼里呢 问你们谁又是好人 谁又是坏人呢 所以不要认为什么东西都是性别对立 什么东西都是啊
The good person suffers.
好人受罪了
Good intentions don't always get good results.
好心没好报
I pursue someone.
我追求别人
So your pursuit has a purpose?
那什么你的追求是有目的的啊
So when we talk about it,
所以来讲的话
At this stage of my life
到你到我这个阶段来讲
you might think it doesn’t matter much
你可能就觉得无所谓了
because after being let down so many times, it doesn’t really matter anymore
因为被坑的次数多了也就无所谓了
you just end up judging the person’s character
你无非就是看看这人的人品啊
of course
当然来讲的话
to be frank, it can be quite troublesome
说白了那真有麻烦
when someone really needs your help
真需要你帮助的人
will you help them
你帮吗
they might not be very good-looking
他也许长得不好看
He might not be able to give you any return.
他也许没有办法给你任何回报
He might not even say a word of thanks.
他也许连句感谢的话都不会说
Would you still help him?
你会帮他吗
If you were in that situation,
如果你处于那种情况下
would you still help others?
你还会帮助别人来讲
And you don't expect anything in return,
而且你不计较回报
regardless of your reputation or loss,
不计较你的名声得失以外
you would still do it,
你仍然能够去做这件事
then you are truly a good person.
那你是真的好人
But truly good people are not many.
但真的好人是不多的
Most are good people.
大部分是好人
I can reap blessings when I do good deeds.
是我能在做好事的时候收获福报
I can gain a good reputation when I do good.
我能在好事的时候收获名声啊
Sometimes when I do good deeds,
我有时候做好事的时候
the sole purpose is for one day,
单一的目的就是为了有一天
if my reputation is tarnished, people will remember this and feel a bit more at ease. My public relations crisis, often works like this. Sometimes, my purpose for doing good is not pure. But this doesn't mean that if you don't have a pure purpose,
如果我的声名狼藉了后 别人想起来这件事会平复一些 我的公关上的危机 很多的时候就是这样 有的时候来讲 我做好事的目的不是纯的 但是这个不是说你没有纯粹的目的
you're not doing good deeds.
你就不是在做好事
It's a matter of percentage.
他有一个百分比的问题
So today we need to understand,
所以我们今天就要明白
in this world,
在这个世界上
purely evil or purely good people are rare.
纯粹的恶人跟纯粹的善人是很少的
There are very few truly pure people.
很少有很纯粹的人
To be honest, many people do good deeds all their lives,
其实很多人说实在的做了一辈子善事
how they fare,
做的怎么着
once you find out the truth about them,
只要你发现他真实的情况以后
they might have improper relationships with many people.
没准跟很多人搞不正当关系呢
Right?
对不对
Some people might seem to only look at young girls on social media,
有些人可能品级上看的都是小妹妹加薇薇
but in real life, they might be very simple individuals.
但可能生活上很简单的一个人
So often,
所以很多的时候来讲
you can't judge by appearances alone.
不能从表面上看的一个问题
Someone who looks pitiful on the surface,
表面上看起来是很可怜的人
might have a heart of stone.
有可能他是蛇蝎心肠
And many people just pretend to be weak and pitiful,
而且很多人只是看起来弱小装可怜
or act cute,
装可爱
they've been doing this since elementary or middle school,
其实人家从初中从小学开始就已经会这种东西
figuring out how to scam money from men,
怎么从男人身上坑钱
but some haven't done it before,
只不过有些人没坑过
so when they do it for the first time,
所以他坑到第一次
they find it quite satisfying.
他觉得比较爽
Some do it frequently,
有的人经常坑
and they,
他
are no longer interested in such petty scams,
已经不屑于做这种事了
they aim for bigger targets. So when it comes to these matters, it's a game between men and women, don't take it too seriously, don't say it's all about love scams now, human society has always been like this, and it will continue to be so in the future. If you can't adapt,
他要坑就坑个大的 所以这种事情来讲 就是男女之间的博弈 也不要把它看得很大 也不要说都是捞女爱情 现在不纯粹了 人类社会一直如此 并将会将来也是会一直如此
then you shouldn't stay in this human world.
你要是不适应的话
It's that simple.
你就不要在人类世界待着了
That's how simple it is.
就这么简单